Guide to the Herb Lerner World War II Letters to Ruth Lerner TAM.194
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Herb Lerner World War II Letters to Ruth Lerner
Aug 28, 1942-Sep 10, 1945
TAM.194
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
Herb Lerner (1915-1972) was a Jewish Communist born in Lithuania, a soldier during World War II, and later the New Jersey director of the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers. The collection consists of hundreds of almost daily World War II letters (Aug 28, 1942-Sep 10, 1945) from Herb Lerner to his wife Ruth Lerner, also a Communist and an activist in the fur workers union (Joint Board, Fur, Leather & Machine Workers Union).
Lerner, Herb, 1915-1972
Historical/Biographical Note
Herb Lerner (1915-1972) was a Jewish Communist born in Lithuania, a soldier stationed during World War II in North Africa and Italy, and later the New Jersey director of the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Roaslie Harris-Lerner, second wife of Herb Lerner, in 1997. The accession number associated with this gift is 2006.015.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of hundreds of almost daily World War II letters (Aug 28, 1942-Sep 10, 1945) from Herb Lerner to his wife Ruth Lerner, also a Communist and an activist in the fur workers union (Joint Board, Fur, Leather & Machine Workers Union). The letters contain domestic and international political commentary reflective of Lerner's Communist politics, and personal remarks, notably expressions of love and concern for his wife.
Harris-Lerner, Rosalie; Lerner, Herb, 1915-1972; Lerner, Ruth, 1917-1968; Communists |z New Jersey |z Newark.; Jewish communists |z United States.; Soldiers |z United States |v Correspondence.; United States |x Politics and government |y 1933-1945; Women communists |z United States.; World politics |y 1933-1945.
- Letters (from U.S.), Aug 28, 1942-Feb 20, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters (from North Africa), Feb 23, 1943-Jul 9, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters (from Italy: Sicily), Jul 1, 1943-Oct 19, 143 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters (from Italy), Oct 30, 1943-Dec 27, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters (from Italy), Jan 1, 1944-Feb 29, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters (from Italy: Anzio Beachhead), Mar 1, 1944-May31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters (from Italy), Jun 2, 1944-Aug 30, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letters (from Italy), Sep 1, 1944-Dec 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters (from Italy), Jan 3, 1943-May 31, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Letters (from Italy), Jun 1, 1945-Sep 10, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)